<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Siv Scripts - Thoughts</title><link href="http://alysivji.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://alysivji.github.io/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://alysivji.github.io/</id><updated>2017-08-25T20:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>MHI 408-DL: System Acquisition and Lifecycle</title><link href="http://alysivji.github.io/review-mhi408-system-acquisition-and-lifecycle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-25T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-08-25T20:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Aly Sivji</name></author><id>tag:alysivji.github.io,2017-08-25:/review-mhi408-system-acquisition-and-lifecycle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of my degree requirements, I enrolled in &lt;a href="http://sps.northwestern.edu/program-areas/graduate/health-informatics/program-courses.php?course_id=4367&amp;amp;term=4710"&gt;Information System Acquisition and Lifecycle&lt;/a&gt; with Dr. Ray Robinson (TA: Eric Abbott) for the Summer 2017 quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course name didn't have me expecting much. I thought I'd put off learning the material until the absolute last moment, procrastating with Python …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of my degree requirements, I enrolled in &lt;a href="http://sps.northwestern.edu/program-areas/graduate/health-informatics/program-courses.php?course_id=4367&amp;amp;term=4710"&gt;Information System Acquisition and Lifecycle&lt;/a&gt; with Dr. Ray Robinson (TA: Eric Abbott) for the Summer 2017 quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course name didn't have me expecting much. I thought I'd put off learning the material until the absolute last moment, procrastating with Python side projects along the way. But that wasn't the case. &lt;strong&gt;At all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, through sheer will (and outstanding course design), Dr. Robinson created a class that has been the most engaging and applicable experience of my grad school career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Course Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MHI 408&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://sps.northwestern.edu/program-areas/graduate/health-informatics/program-courses.php?course_id=4367&amp;amp;term=4710"&gt;A practical course on acquiring and assessing new medical technology, either as a vendor who needs to know how to meet the expectations of customers and their acquisition requirements or as a customer/practitioner who must know how to validate technology selections and implementations. Topics include cost analysis and justification, economic models, capital purchase, leasing strategies, the application service provider or risk-sharing model, purchase agreements and contracts, writing a RFP, analyzing a RFP response, and industry business trends.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workload&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are weekly readings and "lectures". Lectures are mostly PowerPoint slides you can go over at your convenience. Not a lot of formal instruction. You would think the tuition I pay would bring more to the table, but it didn't take away from the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of Northwestern's MHI classes have discussion boards where students interact and learn in a collobrative environment. This quarter's topics ranged from sharing experiences of being on an acquisition team to debating the merits of different open source licenses. This was right around the time &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6nnxir/apache_foundation_bans_use_of_facebook_bsdpatents/"&gt;Apache banned the use of BSD+patent libraries&lt;/a&gt;; I had a lot of fun researching and ranting about React.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two weeks of class were hectic with two assignments due right away. Week 2's assignment was long (18-20 hours) and there wasn't much direction from the professor. The topic was to write a Statement of Work and it felt like a consulting engagement. Client expects something at the end of the weekend, you're not quite sure what. Make your best effort to get them what they expect. Seemed to work well enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courseload lightened up over the next few weeks as we were place into groups for the remaining assignments. Group work is group work. My group was great, so no compliants from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course built up to a mock negotiation held in the final week of the quarter. Students played the part of either vendor or customer, and negotiated the acquisition of an EHR for a 30 office physician group. This was a lot of fun and helped to reinforce the main themes of the course. &lt;em&gt;Anytown Community Physicians, you may be gone, but you are not forgetten&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assigned Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Getting-Past-Negotiating-Difficult-Situations/dp/0553371312"&gt;Getting Past No&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like every great business book, it is just common sense written down. In &lt;em&gt;Getting Past No&lt;/em&gt;, Ury explores the art of joint problem solving. One of the most practical books I've read;  kept thinking of ways that I should play situations to get what I want at work. This book will be on my shelf for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Software-Agreements-Line-2nd-ed/dp/0314294678"&gt;Software Agreements Line by Line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dry. Don't think there are too many books in this space. Does the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rando Journal Articles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No real standout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Instructors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ray is Awesome. Eric is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They made sure to incorporate the latest and greatest in HealthIT throughout the class. Eric gave a presentation on Blockchain and its Applications in Healthcare. Definitely soemthing I need to explore in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of practical knowledge in this course. How to work on an acquisition team, write an RFP, evaluate proposals, negotiate a contract, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave it 6/6 on &lt;a href="http://www.northwestern.edu/ctec/"&gt;CTEC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related terms: Masters in Medical Informatics, MMI, Masters in Healthcare Informatics, MHI, Northwestern, Healthcare Information Technology, HealthIT, HIT&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="review"></category><category term="grad-school"></category><category term="health-it"></category></entry><entry><title>Flexing my Public Speaking Muscles</title><link href="http://alysivji.github.io/getting-started-with-public-speaking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-31T23:55:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-07-31T23:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Aly Sivji</name></author><id>tag:alysivji.github.io,2017-07-31:/getting-started-with-public-speaking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn something is to teach someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I started creating and presenting technical talks on a variety of subjects: &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/201704-healthcare-big-data-analytics"&gt;Big Data in Healthcare&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/context-manager-intro"&gt;Python language features&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/201706-knights-tour"&gt;graph algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similiar to how writing about side projects on this blog helped develop my …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn something is to teach someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I started creating and presenting technical talks on a variety of subjects: &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/201704-healthcare-big-data-analytics"&gt;Big Data in Healthcare&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/context-manager-intro"&gt;Python language features&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/201706-knights-tour"&gt;graph algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similiar to how writing about side projects on this blog helped develop my problem solving skills, throwing myself into the deep end by presenting in front of a group of people spurred me to understand my topic in a lot more depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday, I gave my first conference talk. Thank you &lt;a href="https://pyohio.org/"&gt;PyOhio&lt;/a&gt; for the opportunity. My topic was &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks/tree/master/data-science-workflows-using-docker-containers"&gt;Data Science Workflows using Docker Containers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added a last minute wrinkle and used the Terminal to live demo my Docker workflow. It was definitely nerve-racking, but it went really well. I had more than a few people come up and thank me for clearing up some of their fuzziness re: Docker. That felt good. If I can help even one person understand, all the hours of preparation were worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I'm trying to say is that everyone should give a talk to their peers. It doesn't matter the size of your audience or even the topic itself, the act of preparation will make you a better programmer and help develop your communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With PyOhio wrapping up the end of my conference season, I have more time to work on side projects and write this blog. In the meanintime, check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/alysivji/talks"&gt;GitHub repo of my talks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will post links to the recordings as soon as they are up on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;YouTube Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/3CKVOPPqW9Q"&gt;Data Science Workflows using Docker Containers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hy-O0Qpr_Us"&gt;A Gentle Introduction to Context Managers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;08/01&lt;/strong&gt;: Added link to PyOhio talk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;08/24&lt;/strong&gt;: Added link to ChiPy talk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="talks"></category></entry><entry><title>Coding in Containers: 30 Day Challenge</title><link href="http://alysivji.github.io/containerized-development-environments.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-28T07:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-06-28T07:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Aly Sivji</name></author><id>tag:alysivji.github.io,2017-06-28:/containerized-development-environments.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm taking an Introduction to Tensorflow training class thru &lt;a href="https://www.safaribooksonline.com/home/"&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt; this week. We were given a choice of setting up our classroom environment either in Conda or inside of a &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since &lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; started getting in my way during this year's PyCon sprints, I have been moving my …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm taking an Introduction to Tensorflow training class thru &lt;a href="https://www.safaribooksonline.com/home/"&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt; this week. We were given a choice of setting up our classroom environment either in Conda or inside of a &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since &lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; started getting in my way during this year's PyCon sprints, I have been moving my development away from conda and into &lt;a href="http://python-guide.readthedocs.io/en/latest/dev/virtualenvs/"&gt;other virtual environment tools&lt;/a&gt; that are part of the Python ecosystem. Still have conda installed on my system (and, yes, the sticker is still on my laptop), but it needs to be &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CaiusSivjus/status/867101730986532864"&gt;activated it through a bash function&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;  gogoconda
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Conda is activated&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now I'm all in Python 3.6.1, &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv"&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html"&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; as part of my default Python install. Even went as far as adding &lt;code&gt;alias python='python3'&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;alias pip='pip3'&lt;/code&gt; to the bottom of my &lt;code&gt;.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really didn't want to go back to Conda for a single workshop, so I decide to fire up Docker and &lt;code&gt;docker build&lt;/code&gt; an image from the provided &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt;. A few minutes (and a &lt;code&gt;docker run&lt;/code&gt;) later, I'm SSH-ed into a container and I notice that the course material are inside of the container with me. That could be a problem... whatever changes I make will disappear once this container is removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated in the Docker docs, the best way to store data is through the &lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/tutorials/dockervolumes/"&gt;use of a data volume&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. a persistent folder on the local machine that is running the Docker Engine. After fixing the &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; and rebuilding the image, I initialize a new container using the &lt;code&gt;-v /full/path/to/local/folder:/full/path/to/folder/inside/container&lt;/code&gt; flag as part of the &lt;code&gt;docker run&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the data inside of my container is actually stored in a folder on my local drive. My development environment, containing all the required dependencies for my project, is completely isolated from everything else on my system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boom&lt;/strong&gt; 🐳 🐳 🐳&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Portability just like that. No more worrying about hardware failures and having to spend hours getting my system back to the state where &lt;em&gt;everything just worked&lt;/em&gt;. No wonder everyone loves Docker!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the month of July, I will be doing &lt;strong&gt;all my development work&lt;/strong&gt; inside of Docker containers. No matter how trivial the task, it will be done inside of a container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure how I'm going to do this at work since Docker for Windows requires Win10 and I'm stuck with Win7. Might have to run a Debian VM or use &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/products/docker-toolbox"&gt;Docker Toolbox&lt;/a&gt;. That's on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to keep semi-detailed notes while I experiment and figure out what workflow works best. Building off a slim base image? Have a "batteries included" ready-to-go container for data analysis projects? Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="docker"></category><category term="dev-tools"></category></entry></feed>